Problems involving the greedy pattern
are actually very fun to solve. Well,
that is when you have identified what
will be your greed criteria and the
hardest part is proving the fact that
your local maxima or your local optimum
solution will eventually lead you to the
global optimum solution. Once you have
proved that most of these solutions work
in a linear time complexity. So how do
you go about solving that? We are going
to look at some of the problems that
involve a greedy approach and by the end
of this video you may start to get an
idea when you can apply this pattern.
What factors do you need to look out for
and how can you start to think what is
your greed criteria and how can you take
advantage of that. So let us dive away
straight into the problems. Hello
friends, welcome back to my channel.
Let us do a quick recap on how the
greedy pattern actually works. The idea
is fairly simple. You are given a sample
space. What you do is you choose the
local optimum solution from your
available sample space. After this, you
take up this solution and add it to your
final solution set. You will still be
remaining with some other sample space.
Correct? For a greedy approach, you want
to just keep doing this process
iteratively. From this remaining sample
space, again, apply the same technique
and choose your local optimum solution
and then add it back to your solution
set. This way you will keep on building
up your solution set and by the time
your sample space is empty. You hope
that whatever solution you achieved is
the global optimum solution also. Now
all of these are words. How do you
actually apply this algorithm? Let us
look at the very basic problem something
that we all have been doing without even
thinking about it. And this is the main
crux of how greedy algorithms actually
work. So let us say I have this set of
integers and now I ask you okay use
these integers and construct me the
largest integer possible without even
thinking what will you do you will pick
up the maximum integer that you can find
over here it is a 9. So what you're
going to do is you will add nine to your
solution set and remove let's say one of
the nines from here. You are now left
with another sample space a smaller
sample space. Again you will apply the
same technique. Find out the local
optimal solution. Out of these inteious
what is the largest? It is nine again.
So you pick up this nine and then this
gets removed. What is happening over
here? After each iteration your sample
space is reducing and you are using the
same technique to pick up the optimal
solution. Once again from this sample
space you will pick up the maximum
integer that you can find. So this time
you will find a seven and you remove
this from your original sample space.
Similarly then you will get a six then
you get a four then you get a 1 and then
you get a zero. You kept on applying the
same technique trying to get the maximum
inteious from what is available to you.
You kept on repeating this and you got
the global optimal solution. You cannot
have a integer larger than this that can
be constructed from this set of
integers. So over here our greedy
approach work perfectly. But the caveat
over here is that you need to be a
little careful when it comes to greedy
algorithms because sometimes the greedy
approach may not be the optimal one or
it may not even lead you to a correct
solution. For example, think like this.
Let us say there is a mountain correct
and you're standing over here at the
bottom. What does a greedy approach say?
If you have to climb to the top, what is
the shortest path? Just go straight
ahead, right? This is the shortest path.
But it is a mountain. So an optimal way
might not even look like this. You might
have to traverse a lot of different
paths and you might have to take
different turns to finally reach the
peak and that might be the optimum
solution. Sure there might be lot
different other ways to go around the
mountain but there will be one global
optimum way which you can be arriving in
the shortest possible way. Correct? So
this is a typical scenario in which a
greedy approach might not be successful.
So you have to be a little careful when
applying the greedy algorithmic
approach. So this gives you your first
pointer. When can you apply the greedy
algorithmic approach? Basically when you
have determined that the local optimum
solution will lead you to the global
optimum solution, greedy approach is
your friend. It will be fast, it will be
linear and it will work efficiently. But
if you see that there are some
interdependent steps, if there are
subsequent steps which affect how you
would have approached over there, then
you might have to look into alternate
solutions also. And that is where other
programming techniques like dynamic
programming come in. You are building
upon different solutions. So this is the
first thing that you need to watch out
for. And what we just discussed was a
standard example of how a greedy
approach would look like. You might have
seen its application in a lot of
different places. For example, when you
are giving change to a person, how do
you start? If you have to give them the
minimum number of currency notes, what
do you do? You start with the biggest
note that is available to you and then
you go on to the smaller notes. So your
greed criteria is I will pick up the
biggest note that I can pick up right
now. If you cannot do that, choose the
next biggest note. And that is how you
can guarantee that okay I will give them
the minimum number of currency nodes. So
all of these are very standard examples
that you see in everyday life. How about
some coding problems? For example, let
us take a look at this particular
problem. Assign cookies. The problem is
very very simple. There are some
children available and they are hungry.
So children one has a hunger criteria of
one. Child two has two and child three
has three. and you have cookies
available. Now each cookie is a
different size. It simply means that if
the cookie size is one, then you can
satisfy one of the children whose
appetite is also one. Similarly, if this
child has an appetite of two, they will
need two cookies. And a child of
appetite three, they won't be able to be
satisfied with the cookies that you have
available. So given all of this
scenario, you have to tell me how many
maximum children you can satisfy from
the hunger. Over here, if I don't apply
any algorithm, I pick up let's say this
child in random. This child has a hunger
of three. But I have cookies available
for a maximum appetite of two. So can I
satisfy this child? No. So I'm out of
all my cookies and none of the childs
are satisfied. So how do you go about
it? You will apply a greedy approach.
What you're going to do is you are going
to sort the children in the order of
their hunger. So the first child will
have the least hunger and the last child
will have the maximum hunger. And
similarly you are going to sort the
cookies available to you as well. If you
have the smallest cookie that will be in
the beginning and the largest cookie
will be at the very end. You will start
with the first child. Now whatever the
hunger is start giving them cookies
until their hunger is completely
satisfied. This particular child gets
satisfied with one cookie. So this is
done. The next child has a hunger of
two. But you have only one cookie
available. Can this child be satisfied?
No. So the maximum number of children
whose hunger can be satisfied is just
one. So one will be your answer in this
particular test case. Now let us try to
look at a bigger example and that will
make things clear. Over here I have six
children available and as you can notice
they all have a different appetite.
Similarly this time I have five cookies
and all the cookies are of different
sizes. First thing is very obvious. I
have six children and I have just five
cookies. In no way I can satisfy all of
the six children. So the answer will be
less than or equal to five. That is
guaranteed. But can you satisfy all
these five children? Let us check it
out. How do you go about it? First of
all, what I'm going to do is I will sort
all of my children's hunger.
They are now sorted in an ascending
order. Similarly, I will sort all of my
cookies also.
Now, what I will do is I will start
assigning these cookies one by one to
each of the children. For the first
child, I take up the first cookie and I
give it to him. His appetite is
satisfied. So, okay, first child is
happy. What about the next child? He can
get a cookie of two. So, he is also
happy. Meanwhile, I'm done with three
cookies, right? Look at this next child.
He has an appetite of three. And I have
a cookie available that is of the size
four. So, what do you do? Do you give
this cookie to this child or do you skip
this child and maybe wait for another
child? My greed criteria says that if I
have a cookie available just give it to
the child and then we'll worry about the
future. So what I'm going to do is I
give this cookie to this child and now
this child is happy. Notice that I am
done with this cookie. I cannot take the
remaining cookie and give it to the
another child. For the next child he has
a hunger of five and I have a cookie
size available of five. So I can give it
to the child. This cookie is gone and
this child is happy. So with a greedy
approach, I was able to satisfy five
children and I gave them the cookies
that they needed. So this is how you can
come to the solution. But the important
thing over here is how can you guarantee
that your chosen greed criteria will
lead you to the global optimum solution?
How can you be sure that there is no
other way to make more children happy?
The idea over here is you need to think
counterintuitively.
What if you weren't sorting cookies? Or
what if you weren't giving the first
cookie to the smallest child available
or the smallest cookie to the child with
the smallest hunger? Think
counterintuitively.
If you give a bigger cookie to a child
who has a smaller hunger, then
potentially you are avoiding the other
children to be happy. So this is kind of
paradoxical. That is why I can guarantee
that if I go ahead with this greed
criteria, I will be able to achieve a
global maximum solution or a global
optimum solution. Don't worry if this is
not clear to you in the first time. More
the number of problems you solve, the
better you will get and you will get an
even better intuition. Let us look at
another problem which obviously involves
the greedy pattern. Over here I am given
a particular string and I have to find
out the partition labels. The idea over
here is that you have to return me the
maximum number of partitions possible
such that no two partitions have the
same character. So what you have to do
over here is you have to separate this
string in a certain way such that no two
partitions have the same character. If
you notice both of these partitions,
they have independent characters. If a
character occurs in this, you won't find
it in here. Correct? Had the question
been about the minimum number of
partitions. What you will do? You will
simply take up just one partition and it
can have all of the characters. Now
there is no other partition which has a
different string. But the problem is not
asking you for the minimum number of
partitions. I want to separate it in
such a way that I can have the maximum
number of partitions possible. So how do
you go about it? Where do you start? Try
to think like this. If I pick up my
first character, then no matter what
happens, my first partition will have
the last occurrence of this character,
right? And I'm going to use this as my
greed criteria. So what I do over here
is I iterate over my entire string and
capture the last occurrence of each of
the character that is available in my
string. If you think about the first
character that is a, what is the last
occurrence? This is the last occurrence
and it is at the position 8. So what I
do is I store this in some kind of a
map. I know that the last occurrence of
character A is eight. Now what about B?
I keep on scanning my string and try to
find out wherever is the last
occurrence. The last occurrence is at
the number five. Now go ahead check for
character C. The last occurrence of
character C is at the number seven.
Similarly you keep doing it for each of
the character that is available. And
notice you can just do it in one
iteration. You can start going from the
back and then keep on updating the last
occurrence of each of the character.
Right? So once you have built this
entire map, how can you go about solving
this problem? What I do is I start off
with my first character that is
available. I start off with the
character A. I can check my map. I know
that the last occurrence of A is 8. So
no matter what happens, my first
partition has to be up to the length of
8 at least. Correct? This is my minimum
length of the first partition. It can be
even longer also. But to verify it, what
you will do is you will look at each of
the character in the partition that you
have selected. For each character, check
the last occurrence. If the last
occurrence is greater than 8, then I am
going to extend this window. Otherwise,
I don't need to do anything and I can
stop right over here. I have found my
first partition. Now, how do you go
about your second partition? I will
start off with the first character that
is D. What is the last occurrence of D?
It is 14. So it is for sure that my
second partition will be at least up to
the length of 14. Correct? It could be
longer and we have to verify it. So in
this particular window I will start
looking check the last occurrence of E.
The last occurrence of E is 15. And it
means that I need to extend my window.
My window size has now increased but my
logic will still remain the same. Now I
will check for F. F is 11 so I'm good. E
then G. G is 13 so I'm still good. D is
14 so I'm good. E is 15 so I'm good. My
window ended. So I got my second
partition also. Similarly what you're
going to do is you will start off with
your third partition and try to include
the characters while looking from this
map. I have left this last partition as
an exercise for you. But what did we do?
Just by applying the greed criteria that
I want to include the last occurrence of
the first character, I was able to
construct this map and then in just a
single iteration I got my solution. So
in the end I have three partitions and
this will be my answer.
From all these examples, what are we
learning over here? We are understanding
that greedy algorithms have some pros
and cons of their own. First of all,
they are intuitive and simple if you
have understood the greed criteria and
they can be efficient and usually work
in a linear time. But you must try to
understand that your algorithm may not
always be optimal if you haven't
determined that your local optimal
solution will lead to the global optimum
solution as well. Also, you need to be a
little careful with it. If you haven't
looked up at all of the different
options, just a local optimal solution
might lead you to missing out some of
the better solutions available. And all
of this was just to get you warmed up.
Now let us start looking at more
problems where the greedy solution might
not be obvious at the very first
instance. For example, check out this
particular problem gas station. Over
here you are given let us say n number
of positions. Each position is a gas
station and this is the available gas at
each of the stations. You are given one
more array. This array tells you the
cost required to travel from one gas
station to the other. So for example, if
you are at this particular gas station,
you can only fill gas up to one unit and
to go to the next station, you will
require gas of three units. So basically
if you are starting from this particular
point you will only get a gas of one
unit but to go up till two you need
three units of gas. So you cannot even
travel over there. You will run out of
gas in the middle. The idea over here is
that all of these stations they are
connected in a circular loop. So you
have to tell me first of all hey is this
trip even possible? And if yes, you have
to tell me the starting station. If you
think about it, you cannot start from
this station. You will run out of gas
immediately. Can you start from this
station? No. Because you can fill up the
gas of two units. But to go from here,
you need a gas of four units. So once
again, your gas will be emptied half the
way and you cannot begin from here. What
about the next station? Even for this,
the gas is three and the cost is five.
So you cannot go ahead. What about the
next one? Maybe yes because you have
five units of gas that you can fill up
and it will only consume one unit of gas
to go to the next station. So this might
be a solution and if you go iteratively
you will be able to determine if a trip
is possible or not. But how can you
apply the greedy approach? First of all
to determine that is a trip even
possible or not. What do you think? The
most naive solution is that okay to
travel this particular distance I should
have at least this gas. Correct? Think
about it. If I have to travel a distance
that requires 10 units of gas, I should
have at least 10 units of gas to fill
up, right? If the total gas available is
less than 10, then this trip is not even
possible. You can simply return a false.
So the first step is to add up all of
these numbers and check out the total
gas required. This sum turns out to be
15. And you need to check are 15 units
of gas available. So you add up the
total gas also. And this number also
turns out to be 15. So one thing is for
sure this trip is possible. But where do
you start? To determine it, all you need
to do is just iterate over each of these
gas stations one by one. You know that
you cannot start from here. Can you
start from here? No, because only two is
available and it takes up four gas. Can
you start from here? No, because three
is available and it takes up five gas.
Can you start from the next station?
Yes. So if you can start from the next
station, what you need to do is you need
to check if you can reach the very end
of the array. If you can reach the very
end of the array, it means that you will
be able to complete your trip because we
have already determined that this trip
is possible because that is the number
of gas available. So no matter what is
the distribution of gas in all of these
stations, I will still be able to
complete my trip, if I can start from
any of this particular index and reach
the very end. So once again the greedy
criteria came to my rescue. The next
problem I want to talk about is the jump
game problem. You are given a certain
array and I am standing over here at the
first position. Each of these numbers
they represent the maximum number of
jump I can take from this particular
position. It means that if I'm standing
here I can just take a maximum of one
jump. If I'm standing over here I can
take a maximum of two jump. I can either
take a one jump or I can take a jump of
two. If I'm standing here then I can
take a maximum of five jumps. And it is
up to me where do I want to go. It is up
to me how many jumps do I want to make.
Now you have to tell me if I can reach
the last possible position or not. So
how do you go about it? How do you find
out if it is even possible? To simplify
this problem, we are going to look at an
even simpler test case. This array is
very small. And if you notice, there are
no zeros in the array. So what does this
tell you? It simply means that if I'm
allowed to take any number of jumps and
none of the element is zero from each of
the place I will be able to take a jump
of at least one correct and no matter
whatever these numbers are I will always
be able to reach the end. So you can
straight away dismiss one of the cases
if none of the numbers are zero then you
can always reach the very end. So one
thing is completely sorted. Now what
about this particular specific case?
What do you do over here? What I can do
is I can start to look from the very
end. I have to reach over here. Correct?
Now try to start going back. If I was
standing at this particular position,
then can you reach at the very end? Yes.
Because after this none of the numbers
are zero. So will it be safe to narrow
down the problem to this criteria that
if I'm able to reach this particular
number then I will be able to reach at
the end correct so I have already
shortened out my problem correct now let
us try to apply the same logic can I
reach from here if I'm starting at this
particular number zero no because I
cannot jump so definitely this is not
viable can you go to the last position
if You're here once again. No. Can you
go to the last position if you are at
one? No, because from here you can only
take a maximum jump of one. So, keep
going back. Can you reach from here once
again? No, because from here you can
only take a maximum jump of two. Keep
going back. Can you reach the end from
here? Yes, because you can take a jump
of five. So, one won't work. Two won't
work. Three? No. Four? No. How about
five? Yes. So if I can somehow reach
this particular position, I will be able
to reach my very end. And if I am here,
I can reach the very end of the array
also. Right? So what I just did, I
narrowed down my problem once again. If
I can reach this particular position,
then I can straight away reach the last
position also. So what I'm doing for
every iteration I am trying to narrow
down my search space and I am applying
the same greed criteria. If I can reach
here then I can reach here and then I
can reach here also. So as I don't have
any zeros available I know that I can
reach this particular number and then I
can reach here and then I can reach
here. So once again I can say that yes I
am able to reach the last position and
once again I use the greedy criteria.
Over here you just had to find out if a
jump to the last position was possible
or not. There is one more variation
available of the problem where you have
to tell me the minimum number of jumps
required to reach the very end. And once
again greedy approach is your friend
over there. What you basically do is
your greed criteria will be what is the
maximum jump or what is the maximum
window available where you can land from
your current sample space. So that's how
I will start. For example, this is my
current sample space. I can only advance
one other position. So this will give me
one more sample window. In this sample
window, how far can I go? Once again, I
can only jump one more position. So
that's it. Now what about this window?
From this particular window, how far can
I jump? I can jump a maximum of two
spaces.
So this is my new sample space. What are
we doing over here? We are doing the
jumps required. So up till now I started
from here. So one jump then two jump and
this is the third jump. In my next jump
I will have to choose from this
particular sample space. So if I can
take five jumps, this is the maximum
that I go. If I take two jumps, this is
the maximum that I can get. What is this
telling me? It is giving me the next
possible window. So in the next possible
window, I will have all of these numbers
available. And now once again repeat the
same process for this window. Now
determine how far can you go. This will
only land you here. These two numbers
won't land you anywhere. This number
will land you over here. So this is
giving me my last jump that I will have
to take and that is how you will reach
your end. So how many jumps did you
take? You took a total of 1 2 3 4 and
then a five. The minimum required jumps
are five. So once again your greet
criteria defines how will you approach
the problem and how can you arrive at
the most efficient solution. You might
have to think why is this local optimum
solution the global optimum solution
because when you are starting from a
particular space you want to maximize
how far you can reach. So this is the
thought if you are finding a solution
other than this thought then you are not
finding the minimum jumps because if you
want to go farest in the minimum number
of jumps you will have to look at the
maximum range you can cover. So this
thought aligns with the global optimum
solution and hence it is valid. One last
problem that I want to cover is non-over
overlapping intervals and no greedy
approach will be complete without this.
Probably this is one of the first
problems that start to get tricky and
you realize okay greedy approach is
actually something. What you are given
over here is you are given certain
amount of course schedules or rather
some intervals. So this is a problem
written in a lot of different words like
these are activities, these are
syllabus, these are your courses, these
are your day schedules. It could be
anything. The idea is that you are given
this particular time range and each
activity has a certain span available.
For example, this activity will take 2
hours. This will take 1 hour. This
activity is going to take 4 hours. So
you have to tell me the maximum number
of activities or the maximum number of
intervals that you can choose such that
none of the intervals are overlapping.
Because if you think about it, if you're
doing this particular activity, this
activity starts in the middle. So you
cannot take two activities at once. So
either you will have to choose this or
you will have to choose this. The
problem says that I have to find the
maximum number of activities that I can
finish. Once again, you have to apply
the greedy criteria. But what is your
greedy criteria? One thought immediately
comes to your mind is okay, I will want
to start my activity as soon as possible
because I don't want to waste any time
of the day. Correct? But this approach
won't give you the optimal solution
because you are right. You don't want to
waste any time in the start of the day.
You want to start an activity as early
as possible. But your objective over
here is not to waste time in the
beginning. Your objective over here is
to complete as many number of activities
as possible. So your greed criteria
should be different. You should be
looking for activities that immediately
end. You should be looking for
activities that end the soonest. So it
gives you more room in the future to
take on more activities. Think like
this. If I am able to complete any
activity pretty soon, let us say I have
24 hours in a day. If I complete the one
activity by 2:00, then I have the whole
day remaining to cover more activities.
However, if I look for the very first
activity that is available, it could be
possible that this activity is for 6
hours. So I have very less room
available. That is your criteria. So
what do we do? I have all of these
activities and I have the ending time of
all of these activities. This ends at
four, this six, this 8, this 8, this
five, and then seven. Again, what you
want to do is you want to sort using the
end time of each of the activities. When
you sort this, your activities or your
intervals start to look like this. This
activity ends at four, then five, then
six, and then seven, and then eight. So
this is the idea that I'm going to use.
I will take up whatever activity comes
to me or whatever activity ends the
earliest out of all of these activities.
This activity ends the earliest. So I
will pick this. As soon as you pick this
immediately you will be able to negate
some of the activities because think
about it this activity overlaps so you
cannot do it. This activity overlaps so
you cannot do it. So eventually what
will happen is these activities will go
out of your schedule. I am at 4 p.m. and
I completed my activity. What next? You
have to choose again. So once again go
for the activity that ends the earliest
because that was my grade criteria and
it has to be applied at every iteration.
This time no activity ends at 5, no
activity ends at 6, but I have an
activity that is ending at 7. So I will
keep this activity and this activity is
negated because it is overlapping. So
I'm going to remove it from my schedule.
This activity ends here. And now what I
have once again check do you have any
activity that is ending soon? This
particular activity ends at 8. So I will
take this activity in my schedule and
this is my final schedule for the day.
This is the maximum number of intervals
that I will have such that they are not
overlapping. No other approach is going
to give you more intervals than this.
And try to think why was the greedy
approach optimal over here? Because we
are trying to free up our time in the
day. So this is just a kind of scenario
that you learn when you solve more and
more problems. So if I have to summarize
everything, this is how I would look at
greedy patterns. First of all, identify
your optimization goal. You have to
maximize something or you have to
minimize something. Next, you need to
make sure that whatever local optimus
solution you're picking up, it should
not affect the global optimus solution.
This is really essential and once you
have determined it, once you have proved
it, then you can start to think about a
greedy approach. What you next do is
mostly sorting will help because once
you have sorted things you get some kind
of an indication how to proceed. You
know that greedy approaches usually work
in a linear time. So you have to start
somewhere and then go all the way up to
end. And sorting usually categorizes and
groups all of the data together. So that
comes in really handy. And I would say
that this middle step might be optional.
It is based upon the greed strategy that
you're choosing. This is also very
essential. Your greed criteria should
ensure that you are reaching the global
optimum solution. It should not be that
okay I will pick this criteria because
it seems suitable to me. You have to try
and prove its mathematical correctness.
You have to try other greed criterias
also because it is not necessary that
the first thought that comes to your
mind is the efficient one. Once you have
done all of it, just keep on iterating
and you will be able to prove the
correctness. Try counterintuitive ideas.
Try to find a thought that is going to
contradict your actual hypothesis and
you will be able to prove by fallacy
that the solution that you're discussing
or that the solution that you are
thinking of is in fact the correct
solution. I know that a greedy algorithm
doesn't come straight to your mind. It
is not something that you can learn. It
just comes with more and more practice
and with more and more problems that you
see. Sometimes a solution that may
appear brute force or a solution that
comes to your mind in the first glance
that is in fact the most optimal
solution and that is what makes greedy
patterns so interesting and they're
always fun to solve. Interviewers love
it because the code written for them is
pretty small and they will be able to
negotiate on it and they will be able to
ask a lot of questions to you on it
because the code is small. It gives you
time over telephonic interviews. It
gives you time in inerson interviews as
well because nobody likes to debug or
read a code written for graphs and
trees, right? So tell me all of your
thoughts. What do you feel about the
video? What problems did you have? Tell
me all of the greedy pattern problems
that you have seen and the comment
section will actually become a very good
collection of all of the different types
of problems. Let me know what other
patterns have you seen and how do you
approach the problem. I would be happy
to discuss all of it with you. As a
reminder, if you found this video
helpful, please do consider subscribing
to my channel and share this video with
your friends. This really keeps me
motivated and I can make more such
videos. Also, a huge shout out to all of
the members who support my channel. You
guys really keep me going and as a
member you do get prior to reply to your
comments and early access to new videos
as well. Also remember you can now
schedule a onetoone session with me and
we can discuss about almost anything.
Stay tuned for my upcoming video. Until
then see you.